Finding Aid to the Gloria Steinem papers SSC.MS.00237
Sophia Smith Collection
Gloria Steinem papers
1940 - 2000
Sophia Smith Collection
Steinem, Gloria
SSC.MS.00237
237 boxes (105.75 linear feet)
Journalist; feminist; political activist; co-founder, Ms magazine; co-founder, Women's Action Alliance; co-founder, Ms Foundation for Women; and co-founder, National Women's Political Caucus. In addition to providing a complete picture of the life of an important feminist leader, the Gloria Steinem Papers document women at the grassroots level of the feminist movement, whose letters to Steinem demonstrate her role as a symbol of the changes they were experiencing in their own lives. The papers also document Steinem's friendships and work with African-American feminists Shirley Chisholm, Florynce Kennedy and Dorothy Pitman Hughes; lesbian activists Andrea Dworkin and Kate Millett; and labor organizers such as Dolores Huerta and Karen Nussbaum. Material in the collection includes correspondence, writings, speeches, subject files, memorabilia, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Gloria Steinem was born on March 25, 1934 in Toledo, Ohio to Leo Steinem and Ruth Nuneviller Steinem, the second of their two children (Suzanne Steinem was born in 1925). She grew up in Toledo and Clark Lake, Michigan, where the family ran a summer resort. Leo and Ruth divorced in 1945, and, with Suzanne away at Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts, eleven-year-old Gloria assumed responsibility for the care of her mother, who was increasingly vulnerable to mental illness. For a short time Gloria lived with Suzanne, by that time employed in Washington, D.C., completing her senior year at Western High School in Georgetown.
In 1952, Steinem followed Suzanne to Smith College. After her 1956 graduation, Steinem received a Chester Bowles post-graduate fellowship to spend two years studying and writing in India, where she absorbed grass roots organizing skills from followers of Gandhi. In 1960 she moved to New York City where she worked for Help! magazine and wrote freelance for Life, Esquire, Glamour, and many other newspapers and magazines. Steinem co-founded New York magazine in 1968 and served as its political columnist until 1972. She was active in various civil rights and peace campaigns in the 1960s and 70s, including United Farmworkers, Vietnam War Tax Protest, and Committee for the Legal Defense of Angela Davis. She also participated in the political campaigns of Adlai Stevenson, Robert Kennedy, Shirley Chisholm, and many others.
Steinem came to the Women's Movement in 1969, after she attended a meeting of the Redstockings during which women shared their experiences with abortion. Her consciousness raised, she began speaking to audiences across the country, often paired with African-American activist Dorothy Pitman Hughes, and later Florynce Kennedy and Margaret Sloan. In 1971, Steinem, with others, founded Ms. magazine, and since that time, Steinem has devoted her career to writing, editing, fund-raising, and publicity on behalf of Ms, its allied organizations (e.g. the Ms. Foundation for Women, the Free to Be Foundation) and the women's movement more generally. A collection of her Ms. articles and other work was published in a best selling book, Outrageous Acts and Everyday Rebellions (1983). She published Marilyn in 1986, Revolution from Within in 1992, and Moving Beyond Words in 1994. In 1986, Steinem became a contributing correspondent for the Today Show, doing interviews and features. Other organizing activities include the founding of the Ms. Foundation for Women, The National Women's Political Caucus, Voters for Choice, The Women's Action Alliance, and the Coalition of Labor Union Women. She has lectured extensively and received numerous writing awards, including the Front Page, Clarion, and Penney- Missouri journalism awards. Bloomfield College, Simmons College, Smith College, the University of Toledo, and Hobart and William Smith College have awarded Steinem honorary degrees.
Two book-length biographies of Steinem have appeared to date: Carolyn Heilbrun, The Education of a Woman: The Life of Gloria Steinem (1995); and Sydney Stern, Gloria Steinem: Her Passions, Politics and Mystique (1997).
Scope and Contents
The Gloria Steinem Papers (105.75 linear feet, circa 1940-97) offer an extraordinarily complete picture of an important feminist leader's public life, and to some extent her private life as well, but there is much more here than the raw material for Steinem's biography. The correspondence, writings, speeches, subject files, memorabilia, photographs, and other papers collected here document the Women's Movement from the standpoint of not only the movers and shakers, but also the individual women at the grass roots level whose letters to Steinem indicate the ways in which they responded to her as a symbol of the changes they were experiencing in their own lives. The papers also reflect the diversity of the modern women's movement. Steinem's ability to form productive alliances with women of different races and classes reflect her commitment to their concerns. Within the papers is evidence of her friendships and political work with pioneering African-American feminists such as Florynce Kennedy and Dorothy Pitman Hughes; lesbian authors and activists Andrea Dworkin, Rita Mae Brown, and Kate Millett; and labor organizers such as the United Farmworkers' Dolores Huerta and Karen Nussbaum of SEIU, District 925. Her importance as a founder, editor, and key fund-raiser for Ms. magazine make this collection central to the study of late 20th century journalism. Steinem's papers will be essential to any serious scholarly work on the women's liberation movement and twentieth century feminism.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into ten series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Speeches and Appearances
IV. Writings
V. Organizations
VI. Political Campaigns
VII. Subjects
VIII. Photographs
IX. Audiovisual Material
X. Oversize Material
Additional Formats
Selections from the Gloria Steinem Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit Agents of Social Change: New Resources on 20th-century Women's Activism.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Ms. Records (unprocessed) and the Women's Action Alliance Records, Sophia Smith Collection.
See also Revealing Women's Life Stories: Papers from the 50th Anniversary Celebration of the Sophia Smith Collection for article on Gloria Steinem by Carolyn Heilbrun.
Conditions Governing Access
The processed portions of the Gloria Steinem Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, with the following exceptions:
Financial and legal records are closed until 2020.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
The Margaret Sloan file is closed until 2025.
Correspondence with Amy Goldstein Adams is closed until 2020.
New accessions are closed until processed.
Researchers wishing to consult the Public Response Mail must sign an access agreement in which they agree to refrain from making public any information that would identify a correspondent.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gloria Steinem began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1984 and will continue to add to the collection.
Abortion--Political aspects--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; India-Social life and customs-20th century--Sources; Pornography--Social aspects--United States--History--20th century-Sources; Pro-choice movement--United States--History--Sources; Women in politics--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women's rights--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women journalists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; correspondence; Writings; Speeches; photographs; memorabilia; Awards; Financial records; Ephemera; Audiotapes; Videotapes; Oral histories; CD-Roms; DVD video discs; Computer media; Democratic Party (U.S.)--History--20th century--Sources; Ms. Foundation for Women--History--Sources; Ms.--History--Sources; National Abortion Rights Action League--History--Sources; National Women's Political Caucus--History--Sources; New York [journal title]; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Voters for Choice--History--Sources; Women USA (New York, N.Y.); Women's Action Alliance; Wonder Woman Foundation--History--Sources; Abzug, Bella S., 1920-; Feigen, Brenda; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-; Hughes, Dorothy Pitman; Kennedy, Florynce, 1916-; Millett, Kate; Monroe, Marilyn, 1926-1962; Steinem, Gloria
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1946-96
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material documenting the broad outlines of Steinem's life. It consists of eight subseries: Writings about Steinem; Interviews; Education; Personal records; Birthday celebrations and tributes; Awards, honorary degrees and gifts; Memorabilia; and Family. The series contains material dating back to the 1940s, but, except for the experiences she recounts in some of the interview transcripts and clippings, it includes little from her childhood. Most of the material describes her life during and after college and traces her evolution from a poor Toledo teenager to a successful New York writer to an influential and internationally-known feminist.
  Writings about Steinem consists primarily of magazine and newspaper articles documenting Steinem's role as a public figure and influential activist. The articles compiled in this subseries report on Steinem's activities from the 1950s to the present and record her views on a variety of issues and events. While these materials provide an overview of Steinem's long career, researchers should be aware that additional clippings pertaining to particular events in Steinem's life can be found elsewhere throughout the collection, e.g., for articles and reviews related to Steinem's books, see SERIES IV. WRITINGS. For clippings regarding particular speaking appearances, researchers may wish to consult the folders devoted to individual events in SERIES III. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES.
  The Education subseries includes material documenting Steinem's early school years in Toledo, Ohio and Washington, D.C. as well as her experience at Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts, and the two subsequent years she spent in India as a Chester Bowles Fellow. The earliest years of Steinem's general correspondence, found in SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, also contain letters pertaining to her travels in India. Finally, a folder of materials devoted to Steinem's activities importing Indian goods to the U.S. is housed below, with the financial and legal records among her Personal records.
  Personal records consists of appointment books, business cards, calendars, notes, phone logs and lists of personal and professional contacts and their addresses and phone numbers. These provide a view of the vast professional and personal networks Steinem built and maintained throughout the 1960s, 1970s and 1980s. For a full view of Steinem's schedule, researchers may want to consult her appointment books in conjunction with the many itineraries gathered in SERIES III. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES.
  Financial and legal records in this subseries, including receipts, tax forms, check registers and canceled checks, and bank records provide a wealth of information about Steinem's personal and professional lives and document both her early success as a freelance writer and her growing influence as a feminist activist. Materials here are organized under the following categories: bank statements and check registers; business expenses; charitable contributions; general; household expenses; income and investment; medical expenses; personal expenses; expenses pertaining to Ruth Steinem; and taxes. Of special interest are Steinem's lists of business gifts and business entertaining, which shed light on her effort to build networks in the New York publishing world and in local and national politics. Additional insight into Steinem's financial affairs can be found in SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE-EMILY CARD, which includes a transcript of an interview with Steinem about women and finances, in which Steinem comments on her own financial practices.
  The Birthday celebrations and tributes subseries consists of greetings, notes and clippings, planning notes and memoranda, drafts of the "Birthday Book," and printed matter from Steinem's 50th birthday celebration. Also housed here are press clippings about her 60th birthday party and remarks made by John Kenneth Galbraith at that event.
  Especially interesting are pledge cards to the Ms. Foundation Gloria Steinem fund in honor of the occasion.
  Awards, honorary degrees, and gifts dating from 1958-98, illuminate the extent to which Steinem was recognized and revered as a public figure. The honorary degrees are arranged chronologically, as are the awards and gifts. The latter materials take a variety of forms; some are paper certificates or proclamations, some are plaques, and others are small statuettes, glass sculptures, or figurines on pedestals. For the convenience of researchers, three-dimensional objects and oversized documents are described on separate sheets that are interfiled with the paper certificates in their appropriate chronological position. The objects themselves are housed separately with other oversized materials in SERIES X. OVERSIZE, but the folders in this subseries thus represent the full extent of Steinem's awards, regardless of form.
  Memorabilia consists of miscellaneous printed matter, keepsakes, patches, buttons, and many other such items, including Steinem's WWII war ration book, and a stamp from the office of Cesar Chavez. See also SERIES X. OVERSIZE.
  Finally, miscellaneous material including clippings, notes, and legal documents regarding Pauline Steinem (paternal grandmother), Leo Steinem (father), Ruth Nuneviller Steinem (mother) Suzanne Patch (sister), and Robert Patch (nephew) and other relatives make up the Family subseries. There are also a small number of family photographs in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS.
  - Resumes, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical musings, 1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Carolyn Heilbrun biography of Steinem: correspondence and miscellany, 1990-95 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Clippings and articles
    - 1946-77 (Box 1, Folder 10-18)
    - 1978-85 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
    - 1986-96, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
  - Quotes and quips, 1973-95; undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Research and academic work on Steinem, 1973-88
    - "The Rhetoric of Gloria Steinem," by Carole Grau of Brooklyn College, presented at NY State Speech Association Convention, 18-20 Mar 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "A Rhetorical Analysis of Selected Speeches by Gloria Steinem," undergraduate thesis by Sarah Sidebottom Kearns, Ohio State University, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Ms Magazine as a Promoter of Change," by Faith Dickerson and Janet Weinglass for class in Social Psychology of Change, 16 Dec 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Gloria Steinem and Plato on Economical, Political and Social Freedom," by Tami Doyle, 17 Oct 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "A Comparison of Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Gloria Steinem, by Carolyn Fershtman, 11 Jun 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Women's Collaborative Storytelling: A Rhetorical Analysis of Steinem's 'Ruth's Song (Because she could not sing it)' and letters of Response," Suzanne M. Knoll (Masters Thesis, Wake Forest University May 1988) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - One Woman's Power [biography of Steinem], Sondra Henry and Emily Taitz (Minneapolis: Dillon Press 1987): book jacket, publicity material, photographs and slides of Steinem, interview, and notes (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Interviews, general
    General
    [see also SERIES VII. SUBJECTS--Vivien Vernon Roe]
    - Transcript by Sabrina Freed, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Transcript from "Eyewitness Exclusive" on WABC, 2 Oct 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notes on interviews for Newsweek profile on Steinem, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Transcript by Jacqueline Van Voris, 16 Apr 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Transcript of interview on "Eyewitness News Conference," WABC-TV, 30 Dec 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Freelancer with No Time to Write," in Writer's Digest by John Brady, Feb 1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Transcript of interview for Thames TV, 19 Apr 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Transcript of interview of J. Stanley Pottinger for London Sunday Times by Joy Billington Doty, 5 Jan 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Transcript by Jill Clark of Gay Community News, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Gloria Steinem Examines the Women's Decade: Wins, Losses and Changes in Her Life," People, by Irene Kubota, 23 Jun 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Transcript by Mary Vespa, with editing by Steinem, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Steinem at 50" transcript by Irene Neves, circa, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Questionnaire completed by Steinem for Rosanna Greenstreet of London's Weekend Guardian, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Transcript of interview about Steinem's college years, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Transcripts of interviews for radio show with Steinem, friends, and family by Linda Yellen and Alan Lewis, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Topical interviews and questionnaires, 1972-1997 (Box 4, Folder 16-20)
  - Education
    - Primary and secondary, 1949; undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Smith College
      - General (includes 1953 postcard from Steinem to family in Washington, D.C.), 1953-56 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Junior Year Abroad (Geneva) (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Reunion reports, 1966; 1971; 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Keynote address to Class of 1956 reunion (in abstentia; read by someone else), 2006 (Box 5, Folder 4a)
    - Extra-curricular activities (includes Girl Scout badge cards), 1946-58 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Post-graduate activities (Box 5)
      - Chester Bowles Fellowship: correspondence, reports, and miscellany (includes inventory of trunks shipped back to U.S.), 1957-58; undated (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
      - Independent Service for Information on the Vienna Youth Festival: notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Personal records
    - Calendars and contacts
      - Address card file, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Appointment, calendar, and date books
        - 1960-65 (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - 1966-73 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
        - 1975-86, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
      - Business cards, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
      - Contact information, general and India: notes, n.d (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
    - Phone logs and messages, 1985-87; undated (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Financial and legal records [restricted]
    - Bank records
      - Savings account, 1965; 1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Checking account
        - 1958-60 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
        - 1961-69 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
        - 1971-85 (Box 11, Folder 1-12)
        - 1986-88 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Business finances
      - Expenses
        - Dues, 1959-88 (Box 12, Folder 4-6)
        - Entertainment and gifts
          - 1959-78 (Box 12, Folder 7-15)
          - 1979-88 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
        - Office: general and secretarial, 1964-88 (Box 13, Folder 6-20)
        - Professional image, 1961-83 (Box 14, Folder 1-12)
        - Professional services
          - Accountants, 1966-68 (Box 15, Folder 1)
          - Agents, 1964-75 (Box 15, Folder 2)
          - Answering services and messengers, 1960-85 (Box 15, Folder 3-10)
          - Attorneys, 1967-87 (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
          - Bookkeeping, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 13)
        - Organizational and leadership development, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 14)
        - Publishing: Henry Holt & Co. invoices, 1987-88 (Box 15, Folder 15)
        - Research expenses
          - 1959-80 (Box 15, Folder 16-24)
          - 1983-88, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
        - Travel, 1959-88 (Box 16, Folder 6-23)
        - Wilson Fellowship expenses, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 24)
          [see also SERIES IV. WRITINGS]
      - East Toledo Enterprises (Box 16)
        - Article concerning incorporation, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Bank records: checks, registers, 1986-87 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
        - Expenses
          - Business gifts and entertaining, 1985-86 (Box 17, Folder 4)
          - Charitable contributions, 1966-86 (Box 17, Folder 5a-5b)
          - Dues and memberships, 1986-88 (Box 17, Folder 6)
          - General, 1986-88 (Box 17, Folder 7-9)
          - Medical, 1984-86 (Box 17, Folder 10)
          - Office, 1985-87 (Box 17, Folder 11)
          - Personal (includes clothing, cosmetics, and hair), 1985-87 (Box 17, Folder 12-13)
          - Research, 1985-86 (Box 17, Folder 14)
          - Services
            - Accountants, 1985-88 (Box 17, Folder 15)
            - Attorneys, 1984-87 (Box 17, Folder 16)
            - Answering and messenger, 1986-87 (Box 17, Folder 17)
            - General, 1985-88 (Box 17, Folder 18)
            - Travel, 1984-87 (Box 17, Folder 19-21)
          - Utilities (includes telephone bills), 1985-87 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
          - Taxes, 1982; 1986 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
        - Income
          - General: checks, stubs and correspondence, 1984-88 (Box 18, Folder 7-10)
          - Investments, 1984-87 (Box 18, Folder 11-12)
    - Personal finances
      - Expenses
        - Charitable contributions: letters of solicitation and acknowledgement, 1967-88 (Box 18, Folder 13)
        - General, 1961-86 (Box 18, Folder 14-20)
      - Household expenses
        - Apartment renovation, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - Insurance, 1961-88 (Box 19, Folder 2)
        - Leases, 1959; 1973 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - Mortgages, 1973; 1977; undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Rent, 1965-69 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - Utilities
          - Telephone
            - 1960-73 (Box 19, Folder 6-12)
            - 1974-1988 (Box 20, Folder 1-5)
            - Other, 1960-88 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - Loans, 1964-77 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - Medical and dental
          - 1961-68 (Box 20, Folder 8-10)
          - 1969-88 (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
        - Medical insurance, 1965-72 (Box 21, Folder 6)
        - Miscellaneous, 1956-88; undated (Box 21, Folder 7-17)
        - Ruth Steinem, 1964-70 (Box 22, Folder 1-7)
    - Personal income
      - Earnings
        - 1961-81 (Box 22, Folder 8-18)
        - 1983-88 (Box 23, Folder 1-3)
      - Import/Export activities, 1957-58 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Investments, 1969-88 (Box 23, Folder 6-8)
    - Taxes
      - General, 1958-77 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - City of New York
        - General, 1958-80 (Box 23, Folder 10-13)
        - Unincorporated Business Tax Returns, 1976-77; 1980 (Box 23, Folder 14)
        - General, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 15)
        - Resident returns, 1972-81 (Box 23, Folder 16-23)
      - Federal
        - General, 1964-65 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Individual returns (includes worksheets, notes, and correspondence)
          - 1959, 1964-79 (Box 24, Folder 2-14)
          - 1980-82 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    - Property
      - Florida, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Michigan, 1966; 1968 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Legal documents (includes 1954 passport and petition to visit Patty Hearst), 1954-80 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Birthday celebrations and tributes
    - 50th, 1984
      - Greetings (A-Z and unidentified) (Box 25, Folder 7-8)
      - Ms. Gala: Birthday book (includes typescripts, notes and memoranda), correspondence, speeches and tributes, and ticket sales (Box 25, Folder 9-15)
      - Press clippings (Box 26, Folder 1-2)